Guide to the Mrs. David L. Anderson collection BCMS.0088
Brooklyn Collection
Mrs. David L. Anderson collection
1850-1973
Brooklyn Collection
Anderson, David L., Mrs.
Intertype Corporation
BCMS.0088
1.25 Linear Feet in 3 document boxes
This collection includes material on the Intertype Corporation of Brooklyn, the East New York Community Corporation, and various 19th century Brooklyn organizations, as well as a genealogy of the Davenport family.
Biographical Note
David L. Anderson was born around 1885 in Sweden. Various dates of immigration to the U.S. are given in censuses, ranging from 1900 to 1908. In 1910 the young man was a lodger in a boarding house at 144 Henry St, with the profession of "Draftsman—Electric machinery." In the 1915 New York State census he is living at 235 Walnut Street in Queens with wife Alma and two sons. By 1920 he is on 106th St in Queens, with wife Alma P. aged 31, and sons Harold and "Wilbur" (perhaps Willem) aged 8 and 6. A fifth member of the household is Josephine Peterson, mother-in-law, age 62, widow. Like Mr. Anderson, Mrs. Peterson came from Sweden. His profession is given as "Master mechanic—Linotype."
In 1930 the family lived at 150 Senator Street in Bay Ridge. David L. Anderson was by then a widower. His age at first marriage is given as 25 and he is listed as a "Master mechanic—Intertype Machines." His son Harold, now 19, is a general clerk at Standard Oil while Willem, 16 appears to be still at school. During that year Mr. Anderson made a trip to England, returning from Southampton on the Mauretania, which arrived in New York on 28 August, 1930. The ship's records note that he was naturalized at the Federal Court in Brooklyn on 29 May, 1910.
On October 3, 1930, Anderson married Ruth Hastings Jennings, a teacher from New Jersey. The couple continued to live in Bay Ridge, on 73rd Street.
Scope and Contents
The series that comprise the Mrs. David L. Anderson collection appear unrelated except for their provenance.
Series 1. Documents relating to the Intertype Corporation. David Anderson was head of Research and Development at the Intertype Corporation, a manufacturer of typesetting machinery based in Brooklyn. The papers in series 1 record social events as well as business operations and activities of different divisions of the company, with dates ranging from 1914 to 1975. This series also includes several newsletters produced by the corporation, as well as annual reports.
Series 2 comprises papers relating to the East New York Community Corporation, including job descriptions, training materials, personnel manuals and documents on the Corporation's leasing of 505 Sutter Ave. The date range is 1968-1973.
Series 3 consists of single annual reports, catalogues etc. from a variety of Brooklyn charitable and educational institutions, mostly dating from 1867.
In Series 4 can be found various pamphlets, speeches, sermons etc, some of them having only a tenuous connection to Brooklyn (for example, the Dictionary of Chinook Jargon bears the ownership stamp of J. Jay Pierrepont, carrier of a well-known Brooklyn name.) The date range is 1842-1887.
Series 5 contains a handwritten genealogy of the Davenport family with pasted-in printed genealogical tables. Two letters dated 1850 were found laid into the manuscript.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series by type.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Exact provenance for this collection is unknown, but it is presumed to be the gift of Mrs. David L. Anderson.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Sarita Daftary-Steel collection of East New York oral histories (2015.011)
There are various Intertype staff members pictured in the Photographs from the Brooklyn Daily Eagle (BCMS.0002)
There are materials related to the East New York Community Council in the Records of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning (BCMS.0039)
Brownsville and East New York Photographs, 1958-1965 (BCMS.0044)
Typesetting--History--20th century; Typesetting; East New York (New York, N.Y.); Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Genealogy; Newsletters; Annual reports; Anderson, David L., Mrs.; Anderson, David L.
- Series 1: Intertype Corporation
  - Photographs, circa 1936-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1.1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes a 1936 photograph of the Intertype baseball team, a 1948 photograph of a "Production Club Outing," and two photographs of what may be the presentation of the Naval Ordnance Development Award to the Intertype Corporation.
  - Intertype parts and supplies catalog, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1.2)
  - Inter-Views company newsletter, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1.3)
    Vol. 2 Nos. 2-10
  - Who's Who in Intertype company magazine, 1928-1957, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1.4)
  - Who's Who in the Intertype Sales Force, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1.5)
  - Who's Who in the Composing Room, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1.5)
  - 25 Year Group, 1937, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1.6)
    Invitation to celebration of 25 years of service from Neal Dow Becker to David L. Anderson, Dec 6, 1937. Menu from 21st Annual Dinner, Dec 4, 1957 at which David L. Anderson and others were honored for 40 years of service.
  - Thomas S. Homans obituary and tribute, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 1.7)
  - Annual reports, 1928, 1962, 1964, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1.8)
  - Executive Production Club rules draft, circa 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1.9)
  - Ephemera, 1919-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1.10)
    Menus, invitations, and brochures.
  - Development Committee minutes, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1.11)
  - Executive Production Club documents, 1924-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1.13)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1.13)
- Series 2: East New York Community Corporation
  - Training materials and job descriptions, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 2.1)
  - Training and technical assistance program, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2.2)
    Lists of available jobs and document, "Proposal for a Training and Technical Assistance Program in the New York City Model Cities areas, City of New York Human Resources Administration, 1969. Includes memorandum signed by Major Owens, Commissioner.
  - Administrative documents, circa 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2.3)
  - By-Laws, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2.4)
  - 505 Sutter Avenue report, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2.5)
    Report of the special negotiating committee on the leasing of 505 Sutter Avenue for the East New York Community Corporation July 22, 1972.
  - Citizenship Education Program outline, circa 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2.6)
  - Citizenship Education Program voter education guidance workshop, circa 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2.7)
  - Personnel manuals, 1968, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2.8)
    Also includes a 1968 personnel manual from the United Negro Puerto Rican Front.
  - Urban Rights newsletter, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2.9)
    Vol. 3 No. 4. Published by the New York Urban Coalition.
- Series 3: Other Brooklyn Institutions
  - Sub-Series 3.1: Reports, 1861-1867
    - Brooklyn Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 3.1, Item 3.9)
    - Brooklyn City Hospital, 1865-1866 (Box 2, Folder 3.1, Item 3.5)
    - Brooklyn Female Employment Society, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 3.1, Item 3.20)
    - Brooklyn Water Works, 1861-1862 (Box 2, Folder 3.1, Item 3.11)
      Reports on the Pumping Engines: Prospect Hill No. 1, Ridgewood No. 2.
    - Brooklyn Young Men's Christian Association, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 3.1, Item 3.8)
    - Church Charity Foundation, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 3.1, Item 3.1)
    - Committee of the Joint Board of Aldermen & Supervisors, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 3.1, Item 3.2)
    - Gates Avenue Homeopathic Dispensary, 1867; 1 leaf. (Box 2, Folder 3.1, Item 3.12)
    - Green-Wood Cemetery, receipts and expenditures, 1839-1861 (Box 2, Folder 3.1, Item 3.7)
    - Nassau Water Department, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 3.1, Item 3.10)
      Made to the Common Council of the City of Brooklyn.
    - Superintendent of Schools of the City of Brooklyn, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 3.1, Item 3.4)
  - Sub-Series 3.2: Manuals and By-Laws, 1862-1867
    - Brooklyn Art Assocation, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 3.2, Item 3.15)
    - Brooklyn Children's Aid Society, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 3.2, Item 3.13)
    - Kings County Medical Society, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 3.2, Item 3.6, 3.21)
      Two copies. Containing chronological list of members, by-laws and code of medical ethics.
    - Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 3.2, Item 3.3)
  - Sub-Series 3.3: Catalogues, 1866-1867
    - Brooklyn Art Association, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 3.3, Item 3.14)
      Catalogue of Pictures exhibited at the Spring Exhibition at the Academy of Music, Brooklyn.
    - Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 3.3, Item 3.17)
    - Long Island College Hospital, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 3.3, Item 3.16)
    - Public Schools of the City of Brooklyn, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 3.3, Item 3.19)
      Course of Study with Instructions.
    - William W. Rose, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 3.3, Item 3.18)
      Catalogue of School Books for sale by William W. Rose, No. 142 Atlantic Street, South Brooklyn.
- Series 4: Monographs and sermons
  - Brooklyn Ferries, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 4.1, Item 4.1)
    Union Ferry Company of Brooklyn. Proceedings and Testimony and the remarks thereon by Mr. Ben D. Silliman. February 1867.
  - The Progress and Results of Emancipation in the English West Indies, 1842; Jay, John (Box 3, Folder 4.1, Item 4.2)
  - Oration pronounced by the Honorable Robert C. Winthrop, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 4.1, Item 4.3)
    Fourth of July, 1848.
  - Dictionary of the Chinook Jargon, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 4.1, Item 4.4)
    Full title: Dictionary of the Chinook Jargon or Indian Trade Language of the North Pacific Coast. Handwritten vocabulary lists laid in.
  - The centennial celebration of American Independence at the Academy of Music, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 4.1, Item 4.5)
    New York, July 4th 1876. Cover title: Dr R.S. Storrs' Oration on the Declaration of Independence and the Effects of It.
  - Brief Reasons why the sufferers by French spoliations prior to 1800, should be indemnified by their own government (Box 3, Folder 4.1, Item 4.6)
  - Address of claimants for indemnity for spoliations committed by the French prior to the year 1800, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 4.1, Item 4.7)
- Series 5: Family history items
  - Genealogical manuscript, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 5.1, Item 5.1)
    An Historical and Genealogical Register of the Davenport Family in England and America compiled and prepared from Ormerod's History of the County of Chester—Collections from the Harleian MSS, Parochial and Town Records in England and America etc etc, by Amzi Benedict Davenport, Brooklyn NY
  - Two letters, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 5.1, Item 5.2)
    W. Ferris to Lorana Benedict.